VARUN **SAINI**

Hyderabad, Telangana · +91 8630682479

varun.saini2@outlook.com · linkedin.com/in/varun-saini-897497157

Professional Big Data Engineer with 1 year of industry experience in Big Data technologies. Proficient in Hadoop, Spark/Streaming/sql, DataBricks development experience, automation tool and E2E real-time data ETL pipeline using framework technologies like Apache Kafka, NiFi, Druid. Dedicated to maintain up-to-date IT skills and industry knowledge.

EXPERIENCE

FEB 2019 - JUN 2019

DATA ENGINEER/ANALYTICS INTERN, GENPACT HYDERABAD, TELANGANA

- Debugged skills in Big Data Analytics using SQL and Proficiency in distributed queryprocessing tool like Spark/Spark SQL.
- Supported real-time data processes running in production.
- Performed real time analysis on data, receiving from "open weather api".
- Implemented SCD (Slowly Changing Dimension) framework using Pyspark and PostgreSQL.
- Knowledge of Spark, Scala, Pyspark, Hive, SQI.

JUL 2019 - PRESENT

TECHNICAL ASSOCIATE/CONSULTANT, GENPACT HYDERABAD, TELANGANA

- I am the part of Big Data C.O.E (Center of excellence) team.
- Working with data science and analytics teams to define and implement business specific data management approaches.
- Developing real-time data ETL pipelines for multiple storage solutions, including distributed platforms such as HDFS.
- Involving in designing and implementing solutions for real-time data ingestion, analysis
 and storing using framework technologies such as Apache Kafka, Apache Nifi, Druid,
 Spark/streaming/sql, Hive, Cassandra.
- Working on "Real-Time Weather Data" analysis business use-case using Big Data technologies like DataBricks cloud platform, Kafka, Spark/Streaming/sql, Scala, Python.

SKILLS

BIG DATA ECOSYSTEMS

> STREAMING TOOLS

CLOUD PROCESSING PLATFORM

DATABSES

➢ NO SQL

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

OPERATING SYSTEM

: Hadoop, MapReduce, HDFS, Hive, Spark

: Apache Kafka, NiFi, Druid

: DataBricks

: Oracle, MySql

: Cassandra, Hbase

: Core Java, Scala, Python

: Windows, Linux, Ubuntu.

EDUCATION

GALGOTIAS UNIVERSITY,

MASTER'S

COMPUTER APPLICATION (MCA) GREATER NOIDA, UTTAR PRADESH 2017 TO 2019

CHAUDHARY CHARAN SINGH UNIVERSITY,

BACHELOR'S

COMPUTER APPLICATION (BCA) SIKANDRABAD, UTTAR PRADESH 2014 TO 2017